<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>My Musings on Music</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</description>
    <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://musingsonmusic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 19:15:48 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 19:15:48 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.1.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How I got into jazz</title>
        <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-story-about-how-coincidences-can-lead-to-amazing-things&quot;&gt;A story about how coincidences can lead to amazing things.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-xOBj9x28df0/U7RhzavFqjI/AAAAAAAABo4/srzLXZOH9uE/
s1600/63.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been too long. I haven’t written a post for over a year. I devoted all
my focus to other things in my life, but recently I found myself wanting to
start writing about music again. So here I am. I’ll write one post a week from
now on, so stay tuned. And please comment - feedback is always nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it’s been a while, I thought it would be appropriate to do something
slightly different. This one will be a personal story. It might be a silly
story, but it is actually quite important to me, so I’m going for it anyway. I
wanted to tell you the story of how I discovered Jazz (and the rest of the
music I listen to today).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be clear to anyone reading this blog that I’m really into music. To
me, it’s one of the finest things life has to offer. The music I listen to and
enjoy is something I identify myself with. It isn’t an overstatement to say
that it’s a part of who I am. But it hasn’t always been like this.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Without music, life would be a mistake.”― Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it plays a big part of my everyday life. It probably does for most
people, I just tend to be quite ebullient and passionate about it (why do you
think I write a blog on it). It fills most of my time - music is around when I
work, study or relax. I love taking time off just to put on a good record, and
do nothing else at the same time. I get a kick out of reading books on music
and musicians. But in the end, it’s simply about the beauty, intricacies and
the sheer perfection of good music, that draws me so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, I listen mostly to Jazz and Blues. Some years back, I actually
thought I didn’t like that kind of music and in a lot of ways I didn’t. I felt
like it’s not for me, because it’s too complicated and I would  never ‘get
it’. I’d be intrigued by it, but stopped myself, thinking you have to be a
musician or special kind of smart, to get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then one day, I watched &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0910970/&quot;&gt;WALL-E&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one scene near the beginning of the movie, a song inconspicuously started
playing. A lovely trickling piano sounded the room and then, the most
beautiful trumpet I’ve ever heard entered with gusto. I was still not aware of
an impact that this would have on me. Then, as the rich, coarse voice, full of
love and romance sang ‘Hold me close and hold me fast, the magic spell you
cast…’ I would start noticing something. I wouldn’t know what it was until
later, but I was moved. After it ended, the music left a profound presence in
the room. I was mesmerized. I kept asking myself “What was that song?”. As I’m
writing this, I’m aware of the absurdity to write down such significance to
WALL-E, but at that time, it was everything. Not the movie, but what it
brought to me. The movie ended, and I was still just asking myself that
question. I resorted to the the Internet gods, asking if they know what song
it was. I couldn’t find it, so eventually I went through the whole soundtrack,
until I came across the familiar sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La Vie En Rose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Louis Armstrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hm, I had heard of him. Well, I knew him to the extent of ‘What a Wonderful
World’. And I vaguely remembered a music class in elementary school, where we
mentioned him in relation to something about jazz. I was a bit surprised that
this was the man behind the song. Little did I know, that this song, and this
musical colossus will change my life. I Immediately looked for the song on
Youtube - I had to hear this magic again. And I did. I listened to it one more
time, then I started clicking through related songs. I carefully listened to
every song, savoring each note. With every single song, I was taken deeper
into the rabbit hole. It was like meeting someone for the first time, falling
for them, and then wondering where they’ve been your whole life. I never knew
I could feel such joy listening to music. Music like this was unknown to me
and I was swept away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus began my journey to the wonderful music of Louis Armstrong and ultimately
to the world of Jazz, Blues and Soul. In the following weeks, I would continue
exploring Satchmo’s music and even after the initial excitement wore off,
there would be a song every now and then, that would stop me from what I was
doing, and just make me marvel at the beauty. To this day, Louis Armstrong is
my all-time favorite musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After falling so desperately in love with his music, I started doubting my
previous decision that Jazz is not for me. Suddenly I was drawn to it. Most of
it was still a sound I wasn’t used to, but I decided to start exploring it. I
watched a great documentary - Jazz, by Ken Burns, which in turn, introduced me
to many important figures of jazz history. I started listening to &lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/11/the-first-lady-
of-song.html&quot;&gt;Ella
Fitzgerald&lt;/a&gt;, Duke Ellington, Clifford Brown, Fats Waller, &lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2013/01/robert-
johnson.html&quot;&gt;Robert
Johnson&lt;/a&gt; and many more. I relished their music. And with every new
artist, every song, every record, one thing became clearer and clearer. I
found my passion.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2014 19:48:27 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/jazz/louis/armstrong/story/2014/07/02/How-I-got-into-jazz/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/jazz/louis/armstrong/story/2014/07/02/How-I-got-into-jazz/</guid>
        
        
        <category>jazz</category>
        
        <category>louis</category>
        
        <category>armstrong</category>
        
        <category>story</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bobby McFerrin &amp; Wynton Marsalis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-D5qdlIIUh8Q/UP6Mt6uzd9I/AAAAAAAABRg/KvokTWlz8Ns/
s1600/533796_10151133921932976_375791819_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo by Frank Stewart&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in October 2012, in &lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/10/bobby-
mcferrin_12.html&quot;&gt;my post about Bobby
McFerrin&lt;/a&gt; I mentioned I attended a concert in New York, but never
talked more about it, so I wanted to do that now.&lt;br /&gt;
Last September I went on a trip through New York, Washington and my beloved
New Orleans (you can check out the photos on &lt;a href=&quot;http://zanderle.com/&quot;&gt;my
website&lt;/a&gt;). As was my wish for years, I wanted to see
where jazz was born. Just days before my departure to New York, I found that
Wynton Marsalis and JALC were performing with Bobby McFerrin. I had to double
check, because I could not believe my eyes. I was ecstatic. Two of my
favourite artists performing together?! What a way to start the trip that was
already meant to be all about music anyway.&lt;br /&gt;
The venue - Lincoln Center in The Time Warner Center on the 60th street - was
so beautiful, sophisticated and classy. Some don’t care about that, but I
always appreciate a nice atmosphere at a concert. The concert’s theme was
Bobby McFerrin’s biography, but I felt that wasn’t exactly the main thing of
the night, it was more of a way to convey this great collaboration. I
mentioned Jazz at Lincoln Center in one of &lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/10/eric-clapton-wynton-
marsalis-play-blues.html&quot;&gt;my previous
posts&lt;/a&gt; and they are truly amazing. It’s a band consisting
of only great musicians and I really enjoy their sound and like pretty much
anything they do. At the concert it felt like they could make anyone sound
awesome, let alone Bobby McFerrin. I am a great admirer of both Bobby McFerrin
and Wynton Marsalis, and this was probably one of the best concerts I’ve ever
been to. In hindsight I would, however, like to see Bobby do more of his usual
crazy stuff and Wynton solo more. But nevertheless, the concert was magical
just the way it was. The band and Bobby just clicked on so many levels and I
guess that’s the result of Bobby blending in more and not doing his usual
stuff to the fullest potential.&lt;br /&gt;
I was so thankful to be able to listen to their rich sound in person. It was
so intense, I remember getting emotional and filled with such happiness
throughout the concert. Ah, I can’t wait the next time I’m going to hear
Wynton or Bobby live again.&lt;br /&gt;
I highly recommend you listen to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PcByeRvkBQ0&quot;&gt;the whole
concert&lt;/a&gt;, I believe it’s well
worth it. But if you don’t have the time, or are not interested, here are a
few excerpts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/PcByeRvkBQ0?t=24m40s&quot;&gt;Beautiful rendition&lt;/a&gt; of George
Gershwin’s Prelude No. 2. It’s evident right away, how well they they go
together, Bobby and JALC.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/PcByeRvkBQ0?t=52m30s&quot;&gt;Charlie Parker’s Donna Lee&lt;/a&gt;, and the
only time at the concert where Wynton and Bobby directly interact with each
other. And it is golden! If you’ll listen to only one song, listen to this
one. Their duet always brings a smile on my face, it’s just soo good!!! I love
it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They performed this concerts a couple of nights in a row. I was there on the
opening night and the video on youtube is from one of the following nights.
There are minor differences, but there is also one major one. On the opening
night, there was Paul Simon in the audience and after the intermission, Mr
McFerrin called him up on stage to sing Scarborough Fair with him. At first he
was really reluctant and didn’t want to come up, and we all really thought he
wouldn’t. But after a lot of convincing from the audience, Paul came up.
That’s right. Paul freakin’ Simon! Just when I thought the night can’t get any
better… Needless to say, it was the highlight of the concert. Beautiful,
magical, mysterious and heartwarming.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/PcByeRvkBQ0?t=1h50s&quot;&gt;Here is&lt;/a&gt; a version without Paul,
beautiful as well.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally some crazy Bobby McFerrin stuff -
&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/PcByeRvkBQ0?t=1h20m50s&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; he sings Beethoven’s 7th
Symphony. I know right, who on earth sings this?&lt;br /&gt;
At the concert I attended, Bobby sang solo a capella version of Somewhere Over
the Rainbow for encore. Genius!&lt;br /&gt;
I’ll say it again, I strongly recommend you take an hour and forty minutes for
yourself and enjoy this beautiful performance. I think Bobby McFerrin and
Wynton Marsalis have some special energy between them and you can hear it
firsthand.&lt;br /&gt;
It’s actually one of my wishes, that they record an album together. They’re
just so amazing together. Listen to a song they recorded together on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0001CNQNU/ref=as_li_qf_sp_a
sin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0001CNQNU&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;ta
g=mythougonmusi-20&quot;&gt;one of
Wynton’s albums&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B0001CNQNU&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HLD8i8CMw14&quot;&gt;Baby, I Love
You&lt;/a&gt;. The kind of chemistry they
have is simply infectious.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about you, what do you think? Thoughts on the concert, Bobby, Wynton,
JALC, the post? As I always, I encourage you to share your comments.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2014 18:42:08 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/bobby/mcferrin/collaboration/concert/jazz/at/lincoln/center/wynton/marsalis/2014/06/15/Bobby-McFerrin-&-Wynton-Marsalis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/bobby/mcferrin/collaboration/concert/jazz/at/lincoln/center/wynton/marsalis/2014/06/15/Bobby-McFerrin-&-Wynton-Marsalis/</guid>
        
        
        <category>bobby</category>
        
        <category>mcferrin</category>
        
        <category>collaboration</category>
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
        <category>jazz</category>
        
        <category>at</category>
        
        <category>lincoln</category>
        
        <category>center</category>
        
        <category>wynton</category>
        
        <category>marsalis</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Salonski - Fauna</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://f0.bcbits.com/img/a2753353365_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m finally writing about a band that’s not only still active but also
Slovenian! Isn’t that something? But seriously, I’m actually really happy to
be writing about someone I personally know for a change. Two of my good
friends are in a somewhat obscure Slovenian band, called Salonski. Two months
ago they released their debut album ‘Fauna’ which made me take on this post.
At first I was a bit unsure how to go about it - should I try to be as
objective as possible or not? In the end I decided I’m just going to write
what I think and not worry about being biased (which I know I will be).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The band went through a lot of member changes through the years, but currently
consists of Domen Finžgar (accordion, vocals), Ines Vodopija (piano), Jana
Arlič (violin), Larisa Petrič (violin), Miha Hafner (french horn), Miha
Poredoš (ukulele) and Žiga Barba (trombone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domen, who is the leader and the driving force of the band, never fails to
amaze me. It seems creativity is oozing out of his every pore. Besides being a
musician, he’s a composer (the whole album is composed by him), a great comic
author and a game designer. On top of his constant artistic outputs, he’s also
a hard working student of Forestry at University in Ljubljana. The variety of
his interests shows that he has countless ideas and that he doesn’t want to be
bound to just one way of sharing them. And it’s not just the sheer number of
the projects he takes on, it’s the eagerness and confidence with which he
executes them, that is impressive. Fauna, of course, is no exception. Check
out his &lt;a href=&quot;http://finzgar.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;tumblr&lt;/a&gt;, to see and follow his other
projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He managed to put together a great band, without which he wouldn’t be able to
get his point across quite as powerfully. All of them are actually an
inspiration to me - everytime I listen to the album I can’t believe that this
unique piece of music was created by a group of students for whom music is
just something they do on the side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to Fauna on this &lt;a href=&quot;http://salonski.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, where
you can also purchase it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the first time I heard they’re recording an album, I could hardly wait
for it and then, when I could finally give it a listen, I was thoroughly
impressed. From the first few seconds of the album, when Domen’s accordion
warmly backs his vocals, I was already digging it and after the whole band
joins in, I knew I was in for something great. I’m glad to say, I wasn’t
mistaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gE1UCtp2d2c/Udm8wIkPMzI/AAAAAAAABZQ/H3ad8Cy2ljI/
s1600/16213_446663092085578_778926986_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo by Sabina Pirnat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The album is truly amazing. Its genres range from folk, etno, doo wop to rap,
cajun and tango, while its inspirations reach even broader. It’s very easy to
listen to and its strongest point, I believe, is that it is so incredibly
comforting. Not everything is executed with perfection and some parts are
modest, but through that it shows the honesty and unpretentiousness of the
whole band. They love what they’re doing and they play from their heart, which
always shines through. The great, unusual instrument selection gives the album
its warm sound. And I must say, no drums is a welcome change from what we’re
used to hearing every day. The melodies are earthy and the phrases are often
simple, but never boring or predictable. Finžgar’s vocals are raw and somewhat
unpolished but sincere, absolutely convincing and warm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said, the range of inspirations is vast and impressive. I love how
Domen in his songs takes a piece of an inspiration, blatantly uses it, but
adds his own perspective and makes it completely his own. He really has a
knack for combining all kinds of genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He says that for most compositions he originates from his accordion playing
and draws from there. This makes accordion central part of Fauna, which is
just great, since Domen knows how to squeeze all the good juices out of his
instrument and bring out the best in it. Other instruments at times sound like
extensions or assets to his own playing, and it sounds perfect - listen to
Shruti Box and Early Riser. For the other part they provide a reliable
background and simply weave the fabric of music, which, in essence, makes this
album what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first song, ‘Ljubezen delala’ was where Domen tried interpreting the songs
differently for the first time (which is why it was chosen to be the first
track). He combined ‘She thinks I still Care’ and a song he and Žiga heard in
Slovenian countryside, performed by a random stranger. Please listen to ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=owWNCNyEuYI&quot;&gt;She
thinks I still Care&lt;/a&gt;’, just to
hear how skillfully it’s crafted into ‘Ljubezen delala’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to just mention the next song, ‘Tango za mentalno mrtve’ (Tango for
the mentally dead), because of the source of the lyrics. They borrowed it from
song by Gravediggaz, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4vLiJIgVlRQ&quot;&gt;1-800
Suicide&lt;/a&gt; (2:45). When you go
through the whole album and search for all the different inspirations it’s
amazing to think how they pulled it off. Gravediggaz is just one example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my two favourite songs (well technically, three) on the album are ‘V
Calgaryu ni letališča’ and ‘Shruti Box’ with ‘Early Riser’. The first one’s
lyrics are really touching and strong and the whole song is in sync with that.
I’m touched every time I listen to it. ‘Shruti Box’ + ‘Early Riser’ on the
other hand, are just great to listen to. I appreciate the development or the
storytelling aspect to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I’d like to apologize to all my english speaking readers, since
some lyrics are in slovene and I’m not translating them. I hope this won’t
deter you from listening to the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll finish the post here, since I don’t want it to go on for too long. I am
considering writing another one about Fauna, going more into the specific
songs and talking about the genius usage and blend of different inspirations
in them. I’m not sure though, we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your comments are, as always, much appreciated. Until next time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2013 19:11:06 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/band/cajun/doo/wop/etno/folk/instrumental/music/rap/slovenian/2013/07/07/Salonski---Fauna/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/band/cajun/doo/wop/etno/folk/instrumental/music/rap/slovenian/2013/07/07/Salonski---Fauna/</guid>
        
        
        <category>band</category>
        
        <category>cajun</category>
        
        <category>doo</category>
        
        <category>wop</category>
        
        <category>etno</category>
        
        <category>folk</category>
        
        <category>instrumental</category>
        
        <category>music</category>
        
        <category>rap</category>
        
        <category>slovenian</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>In A Silent Way</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-zgioX-
rhAYY/UWctQk0KOjI/AAAAAAAABTQ/pU4fCnTemww/s1600/cover_481121122010.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I’m really afraid of writing about instrumental music. Even
though I really want to, basically all my posts so far have been about music
that includes a singer. After confiding in &lt;a href=&quot;http://mitrovic.co/blog/&quot;&gt;my
friend&lt;/a&gt; about this fear, he made a great suggestion:
we would tell each other which instrumental album to write about on our next
blog post, and just do it. It was exactly the kind of motivation I needed. So
here I am, nervous and afraid, writing my very first post about a piece of
solely instrumental music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The album my friend chose for me is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp
/product/B00006GO9Q/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;cr
eativeASIN=B00006GO9Q&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&quot;&gt;In a Silent Way&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B00006GO9Q&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; by Miles Davis. I
usually talk about the artist for a little bit, but if I wanted to talk about
Miles, one whole post probably wouldn’t suffice, so I’ll make it extra brief.
Miles Davis, born in 1926, was a jazz trumpeter and one of the most
influential musicians in the 20th century. For 50 years, he basically kept
inventing new genres and explored jazz in so many new directions (Bebop, Hard
bop, Modal jazz, Fusion, Cool jazz). It’s safe to say that jazz today wouldn’t
be where it is without him. If you don’t know who he is, you might want to
read something about him, as he is one of the most important figures of the
20th century music. Or better yet, listen to some of his classic albums -
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VmaQdPoWVGM&quot;&gt;Kind Of Blue&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9sVapY6JDu8&quot;&gt;‘Round About
Midnight&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=38bShXrS7pM&quot;&gt;Milestones&lt;/a&gt;. Keep in mind though,
that that is only a tiny part of his musical career - what he’s created over
the years ranges far beyond these three albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-B1a2Tm9SnFk/UWctVDOlvKI/AAAAAAAABTY/-svjWC-
iVoo/s1600/miles-davis-by-jan-persson.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;When I first started listening to
jazz and heard about Miles Davis, I just didn’t get it why he’s supposed to be
so good. Sure, I liked Kind Of Blue, but that’s about it. It was making me
kind of annoyed, that everyone was praising him so much. I thought he was
overrated and was frustrated that no one else saw that. Even with this
opinion, I didn’t think his early stuff was bad or anything, whereas the weird
fusion thingy, I just couldn’t take. His &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y7mHNEA7z2U&quot;&gt;weird
appearance&lt;/a&gt; on stage didn’t help
with that. So, very early on, I decided that I don’t really care for Miles
Davis and that I hate jazz fusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years of listening to jazz (but avoiding Miles and anything similar)
later, I suddenly found myself getting more and more interested in Bebop,
Avant-Garde, Modern jazz, all the stuff I thought I didn’t like. Just like
that, Miles’ music eventually crept back to me after all that time. I gave the
albums I knew, another listen and was surprised that this was the same music
as the kind I used to dislike. It sounded differently. I loved it! There were
so many beautiful things happening in the music and I couldn’t understand how
I couldn’t hear that before. Even though I had evidence against me, I kept my
skepticism against Miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when my friend asked me to write about Miles Davis’ album, you can imagine
how I was unsure about that. I thought to myself “how on earth am I going to
write about this?? I’m probably not even going to like it”. Nevertheless, I
decided that, for once in my life, I’ll get out of my own way, and agreed on
the choice. It turns out, I LOVE the album! It’s one of the most intriguing
things I’ve ever heard. As if that wasn’t enough of a surprise, I found out
that In A Silent Way is supposed to be the first fusion album Miles recorded.
. . I was confused, “Wait, aren’t I suppose to hate fusion jazz? But this
sounds so good. How come?”. After a few seconds of thinking about it, the
music took over and it didn’t matter anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OmQwzAsOw1k&quot;&gt;The album&lt;/a&gt; itself is wonderful!
It’s dreamy, contemplative, other-worldly, melancholic, magical and even dark.
I don’t know if I’ve mentioned this before, but I’ve always been fascinated by
dreams and everything related to them. So it’s probably just me, but I feel
like this whole album is about dreams, which is why I absolutely love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first song, Shhh/Peaceful, starts off with just the drums, organ, piano,
bass and guitar letting you look around and get the feeling of what the song
is going to look like. They set the stage for Miles, and when he comes in, he
glides on top of that background, as smooth as ever. Listen to his tone and
articulation. He’s got such control over his instrument, it sounds like it’s
not just a trumpet, but an extension of his thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song then goes on and develops like dreams do. And you know how in dreams
something’s always off and even though you’re somehow aware of it, everything
feels just right anyway. Well, listen how the drums provide a really groovy
and quite powerful beat, but the music itself is so mellow and gentle. At
first it sounds a bit off, but after awhile it just feels right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another correlation between this song and dreams is how many details the sound
has. No matter where you look, there’s always a detail you didn’t hear before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song continues making an impression like that until, just after becoming
slightly turbulent, it rolls off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I was already totally in awe, but there was another part, just
as good as the first one. What a treat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second song, In a Silent Way/It’s About That Time, begins so darn
beautifully! It sounds so optimistic and hopeful, something like a beautiful
landscape after a storm. After you get a chance to really hear this gorgeous
sound, the flow changes quite abruptly and they start building on top of that.
It feels like this beautiful music is delicate and sensitive, since after a
slight change, everything follows. I guess it sounds like, what I think a
development of an idea in someone’s mind would sound like - from that first
inkling to a full-blown idea. In any case, an amazing second part to this
unbelievable album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listening to and thinking about this album was a really wonderful experience.
I sat in a cozy chair, dimmed the lights and set the music to a comfortable
volume. Then I listened. . . I mean really listened. I was shocked by how many
things I could actually hear. If I had listened to this about a year ago, I
would have thought it’s nonsense. I guess I must have had some kind of
invisible earplugs in my ears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forty minutes of this dreamy music went by like four minutes. The whole album
is filled with so many thoughts, feelings and emotions, I found myself
thinking about it for some time after it stopped playing. And I love how great
music inspires me to listen to even more music, which is exactly what happened
in the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest you give In a Silent Way a listen as well. Don’t think about it too
much, just listen and let yourself feel the wonders of music.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 21:38:44 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/instrumental/music/jazz/miles/davis/2013/04/11/In-A-Silent-Way/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/instrumental/music/jazz/miles/davis/2013/04/11/In-A-Silent-Way/</guid>
        
        
        <category>instrumental</category>
        
        <category>music</category>
        
        <category>jazz</category>
        
        <category>miles</category>
        
        <category>davis</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>There Will Be a Light</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.paul-altobelli.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Ben-Harper-There-
will-be-a-light.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Two months ago I began making some decisions about my
studies and consequently I was focusing on college and neglected my blog and
photography. I’ve simply put it on hold. I thought I didn’t miss it that much,
but then, a couple of days ago, I was reading one of my older posts. It made
me remember why I started writing in the first place. I mean I enjoy just
listening to music, but writing about it gives me something more. It makes me
more aware of how passionate I actually am about music and I love that
feeling. So here I am again, writing after a (too) long break. For the past
few weeks I’ve also started doing something new - I committed to listening 2
new albums every week, which means I definitely won’t run out of stuff to
write about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://userserve-
ak.last.fm/serve/_/29762919/Ben+Harper+And+The+Blind+Boys+Of+Alabama.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about that, let me talk about what I’m here to talk about. In 2004 Ben
Harper and the Blind Boys of Alabama recorded an album called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000TDIE7Y/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=
UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000TDIE7Y&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=mythougo
nmusi-20&quot;&gt;There Will Be A
Light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B000TDIE7Y&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;. It is one of my
favourite albums of all time and one of the best collaboration albums I know.
I’ve always been completely blown away by good collaborations. It’s simply
beyond me how two groups are able to melt into one so completely so that they
don’t sound like two separate groups, while at the same time, retain and show
what each makes them unique. And it all fits together perfectly! It’s nothing
short of magical. The reason I’m bringing this up is because the way Ben
Harper and the Blind Boys Of Alabama work together on these 11 songs is an
epitome of what I’m trying to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I listened to this album, I knew Ben Harper’s music as quite eclectic,
but the part I was interested in was a mixture of indie, rock, folk and maybe
blues, with most of his songs being introspective and somewhat melancholic.
Which I love. Here are a few great songs, so you can hear what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cliffviewpilot.com/images/stories/march2003/april2010/may2010/june2
010/blind%20boys%20of%20alabama%2001.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;The Blind Boys of Alabama is a gospel
group that’s been active for well over 70 years now and they’re one of the
best in their field. And if you’re wondering, yes, they’re actually blind
(apart from one member I believe). They were performing in Ljubljana a couple
of years ago and I really regret not seeing them - at that time I had no idea
who they are. Now I can’t think of any other group that would make this album
as powerful as it is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven of the songs on the album are written by Ben, specifically for this
occasion. The rest are traditional gospel tunes and covers (keep an eye on Bob
Dylan’s Well, Well, Well). The moment I heard the first song of the album,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FALuWDPOLdg&quot;&gt;Take My Hand&lt;/a&gt;, I knew I was in
for a treat. What an understatement that proved to be. The album is just that
good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Blind Boys of Alabama create a basis on which Ben flourishes. They provide
a background that’s rich, joyful and full of faith to his emotional, honest
and heartwarming singing. Add to that a great instrumental accompaniment and
you get this incredible piece of music. Here are, in my opinion, the
highlights of the album:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title song, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4-lHWmpVxzk&quot;&gt;There Will Be a
Light&lt;/a&gt;. No words needed here. Just
listen and feel it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Powerful rendition of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RPn8ivGUVG0&quot;&gt;Well, Well,
Well&lt;/a&gt; with some crazy guitar work
on 11th commandment before that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The a cappella song, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ca1vnGfIWVo&quot;&gt;If I Could Hear My Mother Pray
Again&lt;/a&gt;, is simply haunting. It’s
amazing that a human voice without any instruments to back it up is capable of
creating such an emotional work of art. Probably my favourite song of the
album - the Blind Boys Of Alabama at their best, if you ask me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Do you love it as much as I do? Do you agree that their
collaboration on this album is perfect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. Does anyone have any requests for what you would like to see me write
about next time?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 21:46:23 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/ben/harper/blues/collaboration/gospel/the/blind/boys/of/alabama/2013/04/01/There-Will-Be-a-Light/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/ben/harper/blues/collaboration/gospel/the/blind/boys/of/alabama/2013/04/01/There-Will-Be-a-Light/</guid>
        
        
        <category>ben</category>
        
        <category>harper</category>
        
        <category>blues</category>
        
        <category>collaboration</category>
        
        <category>gospel</category>
        
        <category>the</category>
        
        <category>blind</category>
        
        <category>boys</category>
        
        <category>of</category>
        
        <category>alabama</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The First Lady Of Song</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hLvxzTcTaRY/T5cbwILMT1I/AAAAAAAAB9s/M4mF1PXA9jQ/
s1600/ella-fitzgerald-milano-68.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The First Lady Of Song&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up in this women in jazz series is the magnificent Ella Fitzgerald. I
feel a bit intimidated writing about her - she was just that good! Her voice
is probably as pure as it gets. It’s bright, perfectly clear and it’s very
comforting. Her singing is so effortless that she makes it seem like it’s easy
to sing like that. Sometimes I imagine what it would be like to have Ella for
a grandma. Whenever someone felt blue, she would just sing their troubles
away. While I love &lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/10/fine-and-
mellow.html&quot;&gt;Billie
Holiday&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/11/dinah-
washington.html&quot;&gt;Dinah
Washington&lt;/a&gt;, they never make me feel as good as Ella always does. It’s
easy to get caught up in her music and forget about your worries.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to know Ella through my love of Louis Armstrong. As you may know, Lady
Ella and Satchmo recorded 3 albums together, all of which are simply golden.
Some people refer to ‘Porgy and Bess’ album as “Sandpaper and whipped cream”.
I personally prefer the first two albums - ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.c
om/gp/product/B00004RD5E/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode
=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00004RD5E&quot;&gt;Ella &amp;amp; Louis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B00004RD5E&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;’ and ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000084H9J/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UT
F8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000
084H9J&quot;&gt;Ella and
Louis Again&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B000084H9J&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;’. A combination of
her singing and her exquisite voice, his amazing trumpet playing and his raspy
voice is entrancing. Listen to ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ExmoiGZuiFQ&quot;&gt;They Can’t Take That Away From
Me&lt;/a&gt;’ or ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OtG9CnMtzZk&quot;&gt;Learning The
Blues&lt;/a&gt;’ to get a feeling of what
I’m talking about. And even if you’re not interested in what I’m talking
about, just listen to the songs because it’s wonderful music and also because
these albums are probably an example of one of the best collaborations ever.&lt;br /&gt;
For some other Ella Fitzgerald’s albums, I would recommend ‘&lt;a href=&quot;ht
tp://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00000479L/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougo
nmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00000479L&quot;&gt;Intimate Ella&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http
://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B00000479L&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;’ or
some of her songbooks: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0034J
KYZK/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creat
ive=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0034JKYZK&quot;&gt;Cole Porter’s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B0034JKYZK&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http:
//www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000006P6L/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmu
si-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000006P6L&quot;&gt;Gershwin’s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://
www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B000006P6L&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001LOYS8Y/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UT
F8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B001
LOYS8Y&quot;&gt;Duke 
Ellington’s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B001LOYS8Y&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;. The first two are
actually not even that jazzy, so they might be especially appropriate for
someone who’s not that into jazz, but because of Ella’s amazing vocals they
will also be liked by jazz fans. ‘Intimate Ella’ is a good one to get the most
out of her voice, since she’s accompanied only by a piano on this one. Here’s
an example.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read about her life the other day and I was quite surprised. Ella was born
and brought up in poverty and she was actually homeless for a year before
starting her career. She hit her big break at a talent show in Harlem. She was
supposed to dance, but after seeing an amazing dance act go on before her, she
got scared and at the last second decided to sing instead. Best last second
decision ever!&lt;br /&gt;
Behind the stage, she was actually shy and reserved, which I think no one
would guess because she looked so confident and, in her own words, felt at
home on the stage. Singing is what she lived for. She often felt self-
conscious about her looks and at times even doubted her abilities. How can
someone so talented doubt themselves?! I guess she was still only a human,
like the rest of us, even though she sounded otherworldly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your favourite Ella Fitzgerald album or song? Your thoughts are
appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 10:55:46 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/ella/fitzgerald/jazz/louis/armstrong/women/2013/01/17/The-First-Lady-Of-Song/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/ella/fitzgerald/jazz/louis/armstrong/women/2013/01/17/The-First-Lady-Of-Song/</guid>
        
        
        <category>ella</category>
        
        <category>fitzgerald</category>
        
        <category>jazz</category>
        
        <category>louis</category>
        
        <category>armstrong</category>
        
        <category>women</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dave Brubeck</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.blogcdn.com/www.spinner.com/media/2012/12/dave-brubeck-456.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had something different in mind for today’s post, but something happened
that is just too important not to write about. An American piano legend, Dave
Brubeck, passed away today. He would turn 92 tomorrow. He was known for his
unusual time signatures and poly-rhythms. During his 60 year career, he toured
with names like Duke Ellington, Ella Fitzgerald, Charlie Parker and Dizzy
Gillespie. He was featured on Time magazine’s cover - at the time, the second
jazz musician ever to be featured on its cover, with only Louis Armstrong
preceding him.&lt;br /&gt;
Most people will know him through songs like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vmDDOFXSgAs&quot;&gt;Take
Five&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kc34Uj8wlmE&quot;&gt;Blue Rondo A La
Turk&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe you don’t even know
you know him, but most likely you’ve heard these songs before.&lt;br /&gt;
I think he’s very easy to listen to, but he also has so much to offer. I
recommend him to anyone, to long time jazz lovers as well as to people who are
just getting into jazz. He wasn’t being praised so much for nothing…  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His renown, in part, comes from his great album &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.c
om/gp/product/B000002AGN/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode
=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000002AGN&quot;&gt;Time Out&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B000002AGN&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;, which is something
you have to hear at least once in your life, but the reason I love Dave
Brubeck is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B006O9MER8/
ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9
325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B006O9MER8&quot;&gt;The Real Ambassadors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B006O9MER8&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;, a project with his
wife Iola, created specifically with Louis Armstrong in mind. Regarding the
project much can be found in Ricky Riccardi’s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dippermouth.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; and book &lt;a href=&quot;htt
p://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307473295/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougon
musi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0307473295&quot;&gt;What a Wonderful World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http:
//www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=0307473295&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;. I
won’t go into detail about it (I will come back about this as this is material
for a post on its own) but I will say it’s a masterpiece ahead of its time and
it’s one of my favourite Louis Armstrong’s albums.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YtTL-Z5EyEY&quot;&gt;Here’s&lt;/a&gt; a song out of the album.
Iola wrote the lyrics and she meant them to be light and humorous, especially
the part  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They say I look like God.&lt;br /&gt;
Could God be black? My God!&lt;br /&gt;
If all are made in the image of thee,&lt;br /&gt;
Could thou perchance a zebra be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;was meant as a joke, but Louis sang them with such seriousness it brings the
song to a whole new level.&lt;br /&gt;
Anyway, I’ll talk about the album some other time, I had to at least mention
it. If you want to listen to some great music and hear Louis Armstrong do
something atypical for him, give this album a listen. It’s well worth it!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A musical legend left us today and left a great legacy. Do the right thing and
go enjoy some of it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come back for more reading as I’ll do a Christmas special later this week!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EDIT 7. December 2012: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biography.com/bio-now/remembering-
dave-brubeck-and-the-real-ambassadors-21056437&quot;&gt;Here’s&lt;/a&gt; a great article on The Real
Ambassadors by Ricky Riccardi. Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 10:54:38 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/dave/brubeck/jazz/louis/armstrong/2013/01/17/Dave-Brubeck/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/dave/brubeck/jazz/louis/armstrong/2013/01/17/Dave-Brubeck/</guid>
        
        
        <category>dave</category>
        
        <category>brubeck</category>
        
        <category>jazz</category>
        
        <category>louis</category>
        
        <category>armstrong</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Christmas Special</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://25.media.tumblr.com/de5a94de355bd1ad9956f94fafba0063/tumblr_mepw2dl
wCh1rln1mco1_1280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christmas Spirit by &lt;a href=&quot;http://zanderle.com/&quot;&gt;ŽAnderle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why I decided to do a Christmas Special. For one, I
LOVE Christmas. As a little kid, I used to count down days till Christmas and
my birthday (which is near Christmas) one month in advance. I don’t do that
anymore, but not much has changed since then. I’m still a little kid who gets
giddy with excitement over Christmas. I can easily get into the Christmas
spirit and I love it! For example a couple of days ago, the first snow of this
winter inspired me to put on Christmas music and prepare some roasted nuts and
mulled wine for my parents and my girlfriend, even though it was just the
beginning of December.&lt;br /&gt;
And the reason I’m doing a Christmas special more than two weeks before
Christmas, is because I’m sure there are plenty more people like me out there.
Also, I want to give anyone interested in the albums I’ll be talking about
some time to get them (getting them on Christmas Eve is too late).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a fan of Christmas music for some time, but I was never able to find
something good. Most of what I listened to, was of bad quality, it all sounded
pretty much the same and it seemed like it was made in a hurry and with just
money in mind. I guess that’s the sad part of Christmas music - it’s easy and
cheap to make and everyone will try making it, which means there’s so much
crap out there. But fortunately there’s also a lot of great heartwarming
Christmas music, you just have to find it. Last year, as a combination of luck
and frustration, I found a couple of Christmas albums which I just love and
today, I wanted to share them with you. Hopefully you’ll enjoy them as much as
I do and they will bring you some Christmas cheer.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.vinylphilemag.com/images/vince_guaraldi_trio:a_charlie_brown_ch
ristmas.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first one is my favourite Christmas album ever. Most of you will know it,
but whoever doesn’t, should listen to it as soon as possible. Vince Guaraldi
and his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0090X4H0
W/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative
=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0090X4H0W&quot;&gt;A Charlie Brown Christmas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B0090X4H0W&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;. It’s a perfect
combination of holiday playfulness, jazz, warm sounds and of course -
Christmas spirit. It tastes exactly like those roasted nuts and mulled wine
did. It’s on top of my ‘most played albums during holidays’ list. Below is a
little taste of it. Now go and get it!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/7/7b/Wynton_Marsalis_Christmas_Ja
zz_Jam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we’re already at the more jazzy side of Christmas, I have to mention Wynton
Marsalis’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B002SROHI4/ref
=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325
&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B002SROHI4&quot;&gt;Christmas Jazz Jam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B002SROHI4&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;. This one’s a bit
more demanding than A Charlie Brown Christmas, so it may not be to everyone’s
liking, but it’s a great album. It has many wonderful moments like Good King
Wenceslas and O Little Town Of Bethlehem to name just two. Whenever I listen
to this album I feel like it’s putting together two of my favourite things.
Jazz and Christmas. Does it get any better than jazzy Christmas?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cps-
static.rovicorp.com/3/JPG_250/MI0002/454/MI0002454500.jpg?partner=allrovi.com&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still on Christmas with jazz, here’s Louis Armstrong &amp;amp; Friends doing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000005KPO/ref=as_li_tf_
tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeA
SIN=B000005KPO&quot;&gt;What a
Wonderful Christmas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B000005KPO&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;. When I first heard
it, I was a bit disappointed to hear there are only 6 out of 14 songs by
Louis. This makes it more of a compilation with a focus on Satchmo than an
album done by him. Nevertheless it’s a wonderful album that’s easy to enjoy.
It features names like &lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/11/dinah-
washington.html&quot;&gt;Dinah
Washington&lt;/a&gt;, Duke Ellington, Peggy Lee, Louis Jordan and Lena Horne. All
in all, it’s an even better combination than Christmas Jazz Jam - Jazz and
Christmas AND Louis Armstrong! Just thinking about it, makes me feel all warm
and fuzzy inside. The only thing that leaves you sad after listening to the
album is that Louis Armstrong didn’t record more Christmas songs, because he’s
so incredibly good at it. Here’s Winter Wonderland done by him. Listen and see
what I’m talking about.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;http://dippermouth.blogspot.com/2011/12/very-satchmo-
christmas-2011-edition.html&quot;&gt;Here’s&lt;/a&gt; a post about it in Ricky Riccardi’s blog)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for now but I’m not done yet. Next time I’ll continue with other
great, maybe a bit unexpected but great Christmas albums. Until then, tell me,
is there anyone else out there who gets excited over Christmas and Christmas
music? What are your favourites?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 10:53:12 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/christmas/jazz/louis/armstrong/vince/guaraldi/wynton/marsalis/2013/01/17/Christmas-Special/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/christmas/jazz/louis/armstrong/vince/guaraldi/wynton/marsalis/2013/01/17/Christmas-Special/</guid>
        
        
        <category>christmas</category>
        
        <category>jazz</category>
        
        <category>louis</category>
        
        <category>armstrong</category>
        
        <category>vince</category>
        
        <category>guaraldi</category>
        
        <category>wynton</category>
        
        <category>marsalis</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Christmas special, part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://25.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_mef1cyedO41rln1mco1_1280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snowy Snow by &lt;a href=&quot;http://zanderle.com/&quot;&gt;Žan Anderle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a follow-up on the post I did a few days ago. This time around, I’ll
mention a few Christmas albums that are a bit different from the usual stuff.
A kind of change that is very welcomed among Christmas music, that otherwise
sounds the same most of the time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, it’s the Godfather of Soul - James Brown and his album &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000001EFD/ref=as_li
_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creat
iveASIN=B000001EFD&quot;&gt;James
Brown’s Funky Christmas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B000001EFD&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;. The title pretty
much sums it up and it’s quite an unusual combination, at least for my ears,
but that doesn’t mean it’s not good. If you ask me, it’s actually great. There
are a few misses along the way, but overall it’s a great Christmas album, with
amazing, powerful, &lt;img src=&quot;http://www.funkmysoul.gr/wp-content/uploads/2009/12
/james-brown-funky-christmas-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;energetic James’ singing. I
definitely recommend it, if you’re in the mood for something different. Listen
to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W2GD8nQDxeE&quot;&gt;Sweet Little Baby Boy&lt;/a&gt; or&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MUabyfwVDuI&quot;&gt;
Let’s Make Christmas Mean Something This
Year&lt;/a&gt; to get a taste of it. Do you
know the song Please Come Home For Christmas? Here’s James Brown’s surprising
rendition. It’s very different from other versions which is exactly why I love
it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://revivalist.okayplayer.com/wp-content/uploads/ella-
fitzgerald.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/11/the-first-lady-of-
song.html&quot;&gt;The First Lady of The
Song&lt;/a&gt; recorded Christmas albums too. And good thing she did. Listen to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00006
WL1Q/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creat
ive=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00006WL1Q&quot;&gt;Ella Wishes You a Swinging Christmas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B00006WL1Q&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; to hear how classic
Christmas songs were supposed to be sung. Here’s my favourite on the album,
‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZYkjz-
6nic8&quot;&gt;What Are You Doing New Year’s Eve?&lt;/a&gt;’.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, but not least is one of my favourite musicians of all time,&lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/08/rainy-night-in-
georgia.html&quot;&gt; Ray
Charles&lt;/a&gt;. In 1985, he recorded &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazo
n.com/gp/product/B002D3I1TO/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;linkC
ode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B002D3I1TO&quot;&gt;The Spirit of Christmas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.assoc-
amazon.com/e/ir?t=mythougonmusi-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B002D3I1TO&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;. Before this year,
I didn’t even know he recorded a Christmas album. I think I know, which album
I’ll have on repeat this Christmas. The warm, soulful sounds Ray managed to
create time and again, fit perfectly with the Christmas spirit and the result
can be heard on this album. I wouldn’t listen to this album outside the
Christmas season though, for it sounds cheesy at times. But since it is
Christmas, I love it!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blog.rhapsody.com/Spirit-of-Christmas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my favourite on the album, ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/EEeTnZuVcB0?t=4m8s&quot;&gt;All I Want For
Christmas&lt;/a&gt;’, and don’t let the title scare
you, it’s not Mariah Carey…  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your favourites? What do you think of my humble selection? Comments
from anyone are, as always, welcome.&lt;br /&gt;
Next time, since a good friend requested it, it’s Otis Redding (if anyone else
has any requests, you should never hesitate!). I’m Looking forward to this
one! I’ll leave you off with a great song, which connects this post and the
next.  &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 10:46:31 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/christmas/ella/fitzgerald/james/brown/jazz/ray/charles/soul/2013/01/17/Christmas-special,-part-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/christmas/ella/fitzgerald/james/brown/jazz/ray/charles/soul/2013/01/17/Christmas-special,-part-2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>christmas</category>
        
        <category>ella</category>
        
        <category>fitzgerald</category>
        
        <category>james</category>
        
        <category>brown</category>
        
        <category>jazz</category>
        
        <category>ray</category>
        
        <category>charles</category>
        
        <category>soul</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Otis Redding</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blackusa.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/Otis-Redding.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otis Redding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After talking about &lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/11/sam-cooke.html&quot;&gt;Sam
Cooke&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://musiceverlastingmusic.blogspot.com/2012/11/dont-give-
up-on-me.html&quot;&gt;Solomon Burke&lt;/a&gt;, here’s another Soul giant. Otis Redding was one of the
pioneers of Soul music and was truly amazing. He had a signature raspy voice
and amazing ability to convey raw emotion. There are three words that apply
perfectly to what Otis was all about: Passion, Energy and Emotion. He’s
considered to be one of the greatest singers of all time and his singing style
influenced many singers. To name only a few - Al Green, Joe Cocker, Bill
Withers, Janis Joplin, Van Morrison and many others. In fact he’s number 8 on&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-singers-of-all-
time-19691231/otis-redding-20101202&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-singers-of-all-
time-19691231/otis-redding-20101202&quot;&gt;Rolling Stone Magazine’s Top 100
Singers&lt;/a&gt; of all time. He was also highly respected
by The Rolling Stones, who covered his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sW-TtMKBCh4&quot;&gt;That’s How Strong My Love
Is&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=puydDR7gRmU&quot;&gt;Pain In My
Heart&lt;/a&gt; and in return he covered
their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gmnZRBTPzg0&quot;&gt;(I Can’t Get No)
Satisfaction&lt;/a&gt;. So anyway, if you
know who he was, you know exactly what I’m talking about and if you don’t,
then please, read on, because you’re missing out.&lt;br /&gt;
Otis Redding’s first big hit was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jqVrNK4uiB4&quot;&gt;These Arms Of
Mine&lt;/a&gt; but the hits really started
flying about three years later, when he recorded stuff like Mr Pitiful, I’ve
Been Loving You Too Long, I Can’t Turn You Loose, Satisfaction, Respect (out
of which Aretha Franklin later made a huge hit), Shake and others. He mostly
sang just ballads and party tunes and I’m not a big fan of the latter. I mean,
don’t get me wrong, it’s all great stuff, this is just me being very picky.
What I don’t like about those tunes (like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ohkFgdCE2yQ&quot;&gt;Shake&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1ZxN9iQM7OY&quot;&gt;Hard To
Handle&lt;/a&gt;…) is that they sound
quite simple, they’re done in the same brassy style every time, so after a
while it all sounds a bit repetitive. It wasn’t like this by chance of course,
it was simply because Otis really appreciated the beauty in simplicity. On the
other hand, I’m crazy about his ballads. Songs like Pain In My Heart, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TXmLjbTBcdU&quot;&gt;Try A
Little Tenderness&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sJUWn-26jkw&quot;&gt;Amen
&lt;/a&gt;and others are just too good to
pass on. To me, songs like these showcase his singing and his abilities to
convey emotions powerfully. Listen to Pain in My Heart and listen to how he
sings ‘Love me’ or ‘Come back’. It’s so compelling.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1967, he recorded (Sittin’ On) The Dock Of The Bay. At the time he was
already very successful and he was already considered to be a great singer,
musician and a song-writer but this song took all of that to a whole new
level. It was a breakthrough for him as a musician and it pointed to new
heights that his music might go to. But, just days after it was recorded, one
of the biggest tragedies in the music history happened when he died in a plane
crash. He was 26. I’ll leave you with the song and the enticing question “What
if”.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. I wrote this post after a friend requested it. If anyone else has any
requests, I would love to hear from you!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 10:44:45 -0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://musingsonmusic.com/otis/redding/sam/cooke/solomon/burke/soul/2013/01/17/Otis-Redding/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://musingsonmusic.com/otis/redding/sam/cooke/solomon/burke/soul/2013/01/17/Otis-Redding/</guid>
        
        
        <category>otis</category>
        
        <category>redding</category>
        
        <category>sam</category>
        
        <category>cooke</category>
        
        <category>solomon</category>
        
        <category>burke</category>
        
        <category>soul</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
